This is the beautiful and fertile west bank of the Pearl River
On the mudflats
natural wetlands
dense mangrove forests
the wide sea gate and the vast Lingdingyang
throughout the year
people fish for all kinds of fresh delicacies
in unique and wise ways
Episode 1
Fish for Delicacies
On the Lingdingyang Ocean, in August
a tropical airflow is converging
Dachongkou Wharf,
Tanzhou Town, Zhongshan
This is a sign of an approaching typhoon
Dachongkou Wharf,
Tanzhou Town, Zhongshan
This is a sign of an approaching typhoon
Fishing boats from Guangdong, Fujian, and Guizhou provinces
gather at Dachongkou Wharf
This year's fishing moratorium has just ended
After two and a half months of waiting
the fishermen finally have another season at sea
Near noon, fishing boats are weighing anchors and setting sail
Ming and his fellows on the boat
pray for luck in a traditional way
The nonstop sound of firecrackers
conveys their reverence for the sea
Fishery
Although the typhoon is still several kilometers out to sea
the rain has come from the wind
before them
Ming is a little anxious
This weather is obviously not suitable for fishing
But to the fishermen who have been waiting for two and a half months
this seems to be no big deal
It's shrimping season
Forty to fifty kilometers off the coast
Ming has found a shrimp gathering area
A dozen large nets quickly sank to the bottom of the sea
At the moment, driven by the wind and waves
the fishing boat is dragging a 50-meter-long shrimp net
which makes a huge arc
across the bumpy sea
The wind and waves are getting stronger
The violent bumps
are causing a spasm in the stomach
Only fishermen who live at sea all year round
can remain unruffled
A dozen shrimp nets are being collected one after another
and a variety of fishes and shrimps occupy the small cabin
The sight before them
made Ming and his fellows
visibly relieved
These gifts from the sea
have long been common for fishermen
However, unexpected joys do not always come
We could catch more decades ago
Good water quality and no pollution
Now there are so many factories
Huo Yongquan
and many seafood farmers
Even if you can catch some, you can't sell them at a reasonable price
The main species that can catch in these waters
are the natural red-antennule shrimps and yellow shrimps
These two species are not considered to be the noblest of shrimps
but their plump and dense texture
sweet and juicy taste
and relatively low price
have always made them popular with diners
Freshness will determine the value of these delicacies
Ming must deliver
all the red-antennule shrimps and yellow shrimps caught today
to the seafood market before it gets dark
So, after putting down nets twice
his fishing boat started to return
Baitouteng Seafood Market, Zhuhai
Over 150 kilograms of seafood caught by Ming today
was transferred to the shore at a breakneck pace
There is a long-term partnership
between boat owners and traders
The price of the seafood fluctuates up and down
depending on the supply and demand of the market on that day
The seafood is frozen and preserved
in eight hours
people in Tianjin, thousands of kilometers away
will be able to taste seafood from southern China
The fastest batch will be delivered to
all the major restaurants in the neighborhood in an hour
and become delicacies on plates
The sun goes down, and the fishing boats rest
Ming and his fellows can finally sit down
and enjoy the most relaxing part of the day
This seafood may look ordinary
but it is the freshest and most pristine
It appears ordinary
but it's actually the most delicious
Huo Ruihua
The seafood itself is fresh
We work hard and
Huo Ruihua
then enjoy the fruits of our labor
Really tasty
Fishermen have always used the simplest method
to prepare their seafood
Steam or scald them
They believe that this is the only way
to unleash the sweetness of seafood to the fullest
Mangroves, Dachongkou,
Tanzhou Town, Zhongshan
In the evening, the fishermen
finish their day's work at sea
Yet the mangrove fishing operation
has just begun
Li Huahuan and his fellows take advantage of the high tide
to go through the mangroves on their boats
They are preparing to catch a delicacy
that only belongs in the mangroves
The boat is loaded with dip cages
made of nylon wire
Each dip cage is five or six meters long
This traditional dip cage fishing method
looks a bit old-fashioned
but it is convenient
in these waters
There are more shrimps in spring
and more fish in autumn and winter
The sparidae weighs more than 0.5 kg
Yang Daiyou
It's big
Sand shrimps and anchovies are abundant in the salt tide
Giant freshwater prawns and river shrimps are plentiful in spring
A few years ago, to purify the water quality of West River
and to slow down the erosion of the banks by the tides
the local government introduced over 400 mu of mangrove forest
in the coastal beaches at Dachongkou
In autumn and winter
migratory birds from the far north
also frequent the area
The humus adsorbed by mangrove roots
is rare nourishment
which attracts
a large number of fish, shrimps, and shellfish to thrive here
After a long night's wait
the tide began to fall in the early morning
and Li Huahuan and his companions reappeared on their boats
in the mangrove forest
The giant freshwater prawn is their main target today
Dozens of dip cages
are spread over 400 mu of vast mangrove forest
so they had to split up
It doesn't look like they've had much luck today
Many of the dip cages are empty
The net mesh we use for shrimping is relatively big
Yang Daiyou
The mesh is big
So we catch the big ones
We will catch the smaller ones when they are bigger
Today, they only caught 2 to 2.5 kilograms of giant freshwater prawns
According to that day's purchase price
they can sell them for around 200 yuan
At the peak of the season
they can harvest more than five kilograms of shrimp a day
Soon after, the shrimps that Li Huahuan have just caught
will appear in restaurants
specializing in seafood near Dachongkou
Also, Hopping fish and White Pigeon fish
these regular visitors of mangroves and the surrounding mudflats
are popular with diners
The tide rises and falls, and the mangroves
offer different surprises in different seasons
Modaomen Waterway,
Shenwan Town, Zhongshan
This small island was formed by sediment
is called Zhupaisha
It didn't exist just
over a hundred years ago
Most people who live in Zhupaisha
make their living by farming and fishing
Chen Jinhuan is a native of Zhupaisha
Every day, he sails his boat to catch fish
I've loved fishing since I was a kid
Chen Jinhuan
Now I live by the sea
Sometimes it is my joy
If I see, it's time to cast the net
I will go and cast the net
The fish I caught
do not worth much, but I feel satisfied
Around the Qingming, it is the season
for yellow croakers to travel up the river to breed and spawn
Yellow croakers are also at their best at this time
The rise and fall of the tide
and the salinity of the river affect the fish population
Chen Jinhuan can tell the best time of day
to catch yellow croakers
by simply looking at the open water in front of him
Chen Jinhuan quickly found a suitable spot
on the water to cast the net
Hundreds of meters of fishing net
spread across almost half of the river
The slow-moving river pounds the huge fishing net
into a beautiful crescent shape
Then a boat drags the net down
It is a crescent shape. Then the boat drags the net all along
Sometimes the net is dragged along the way
and the fish get inside
Today's yellow croakers are big, nice
Yellow croakers are delicate
Once they're out of the water, it's hard for them to survive
That's why it's so difficult to see living yellow croakers on the market
Chen Jinhuan and his fellows have to rip the net
to put the yellow croakers into the tank quickly
Even so, only half of these yellow croakers
can survive after landing
In the hands of a skilled chef
a small yellow croaker
can be cooked in many different ways
Fry the yellow croakers until they're golden on both sides
Add soy sauce, sugar, and other seasonings
Turn up the heat to thicken the sauce
The soft yellow croakers
absorbing the sauce
have richer flavor instantly
Fried and Baked Yellow Croakers' Eggs
A yellow croaker has only one set of eggs
The chef is carefully preparing the precious ingredients
Fry and then bake
to maximize the sweetness and flavor
of the fish eggs
Steamed Yellow Croakers is the most popular in the local area
Diners believe that this is the only way
to taste the original flavor of the yellow croaker
with its tasty bones and smooth flesh
During the harvest season
the feast of delicious yellow croakers
attracts diners from all over the country
A large area of wetland has been naturally formed around Zhupaisha
due to the tides of the sea and the currents of West River
A rare delicacy
is growing in this wetland
This is a kind of aquatic animal called Hechong
It is only during the short period time
between mid-August and early September
that Hechongs can be found
Hechongs' requirements for growing conditions are almost demanding
The polluted water and salt tides
will make them pop and die
The second day of the ninth lunar month
is the time when Hechong are ripe
Uncle Xiang has been busy all day and all night
in his Hechong field
Uncle Xiang carefully dug out a piece of mud
to check the number of Hechongs
He is estimating this year's harvest
My field is well maintained this year
I dug pits
and filled them all with water plants
I estimate that the annual yield
is about 400 to 500 kilograms per mu
You dig that area
There are many
Four
Eating Hechong is still
a mental challenge for many people
The natives in Zhupaisha, however, regard it as a supreme delicacy
When we were young, Hechong was like a main course
When the weather is fine, we sear them
Chen Jinhuan
and dry them in the sun
Some are pickled with vegetables or made into Hechong paste
Delicious. It perfectly matches with rice
Season them, then stew them using slow fire
until they
Chen Guixiang
turn golden
That flavor
Chen Guixiang
One Hechong can help you swallow two bites of rice
At midnight
the tide that has poured into the Hechong field during the day
is receding at a tremendous rate
Hechongs that were hiding in the mud
are starting to come to the surface
At the gap of the wetland
a large net has quietly spread
Following the rapidly receding tide
swarms of Hechongs involuntarily enter the net
Caught many this time?
Quite a lot
A lot
Many of them in the net
Look
How many kilograms do you estimate in this net?
7.5 to 8
Today, Hechong is increasingly rare
and in short supply
That's why its market price is so high
The purchase price is above 35 to 40 yuan per kilogram
Once inside the restaurant
the price of Hechong can reach over a hundred yuan
The most expensive worm of all
Hechong can be cooked in a variety of ways
among which Stir-fried Hechong
is a classic dish in Zhupaisha
Stir-fry the pre-cooked Hechongs with various seasonings
Half an hour later
Hechongs are dry
golden and aromatic
The three-hour-long Hechong catching operation
ended at 4 am
Tonight, Uncle Xiang caught over fifty kilograms of Hechongs
His year-long wait has finally paid off
Ming's harvest yesterday
is not enough to cover the day's expenses
So after a short night's rest
he set sail again on his fishing boat
In the interval before the typhoon hit
he hopes to make up for some of the losses
In the evening, the sound of oars striking the water
is particularly clear in the quiet mangroves
Li Huahuan and his fellows
begin to repeat the daily catch
They believe that
if they wait, there is hope
Chen Jinhuan is taking advantage of the fierce midday sun
to dry the unsold yellow croakers
The dried yellow croaker is also a delicacy in the off-season
Uncle Xiang is looking forward to
another good Hechong harvest next year
When people enjoy these delicacies
they can hardly imagine
the amount of hard work and sweat behind
And for the rivers and oceans before us
all we have to do is give back
Next Episode Preview:
Taste Zhongshan 2
The mild climate
Next Episode Preview:
Taste Zhongshan 2
and the abundant rain
Next Episode Preview:
Taste Zhongshan 2
make the hills here
Next Episode Preview:
Taste Zhongshan 2
an ideal place for many ingredients of food to grow
Next Episode Preview:
Taste Zhongshan 2
Throughout the year
Next Episode Preview:
Taste Zhongshan 2
the people of the hills and forests are adapted to the season
Next Episode Preview:
Taste Zhongshan 2
They pick, catch and dig
Next Episode Preview:
Taste Zhongshan 2
preparing a wide range of
Next Episode Preview:
Taste Zhongshan 2
nature-inspired delicacies
Next Episode Preview:
Taste Zhongshan 2